Guide to the Higley Hill Camp Photographs PHOTOS.269
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Higley Hill Camp Photographs
1940s-1997
1940-1969
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Higley Hill Camp (Wilmington, Vt.)
Gerson, Paula Lieber
Levy, Linda Lieber
PHOTOS.269
0.75 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 negatives box.
Higley Hill Camp, a left-wing summer camp for children in Wilmington, Vermont, was owned and operated by Max and Grace Granich, who had been active in the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) in the years before opening the camp. This collection contains black and white photographs and negatives, slides, brochures, and holiday greeting cards from the Camp, during the late 1940s to the late 1960s,that show children and adults engaged in activities at Higley Hill Camp as well as group shots and portraits of campers and staff. Also documented is a fire that took place at the camp in 1948.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were separated from The Higley Hill Hill Camp Records (TAM 447). The images in this collection were part of a larger donation of materials by Linda Lieber Levy and Paula Lieber Gerson in 2009. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2012.067 and NPA.2009.011.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Higley Hill Camp, a left-wing summer camp for children in Wilmington, Vermont, was owned and operated by Max and Grace Granich. Max Granich joined the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) in the late 1920s; he also served as chauffeur and bodyguard for Earl Browder, General Secretary of the CPUSA, and as Managing Editor of China Today. Grace Granich was a key administrative figure in the national office of the CPUSA from 1930 to 1945, serving as secretary to Browder and as a member of its Organization Department. Following the postwar expulsion of Browder from the CPUSA, the Graniches distanced themselves from the Communist Party and in 1946 opened Higley Hill Camp, which they ran until 1964.
Paula Lieber Gerson and Linda Lieber Levy are sisters and former Higley Hill campers. Gerson is a professor of Art History. Gerson and Levy and their husbands, Bill and Alex, managed Higley Hill for a number of years after the Graniches retired until the Graniches sold the camp. After Higley Hill was sold, the Levys opened their own summer camp, Apple Hill, which many former Higley Hill campers attended.
Related Archival Materials
Marion Nestle Higley Hill Camp Photographs (PHOTOS 239); Peter Hall Higley Hill Camp Photographs (PHOTOS 271); Higley Hill Camp Records (TAM 447); Grace and Max Granich Papers (TAM 255).
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains black and white photographs and negatives, slides, brochures, and holiday greeting cards from the Higley Hill Camp, from the late 1940s and late 1960s, with the bulk of the materials from 1957-1966. These images show children and adults engaged in activities at the camp, as well as group shots and portraits of campers and staff; they also document a fire that took place at the camp in 1948.
Arrangement
The Higley Hill Camp Photographs Collection is arranged into two series by format:
Series I - Photographs, Negatives, and Ephmera.
Series II - 70mm Slides.
Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Color slides.; Photographs.; Camps |z Vermont.; Black-and-white negatives.; Gerson, Paula Lieber; Levy, Linda Lieber; Granich, Max, 1896-1987; Granich, Grace, 1895-1971
- Series I - Photographs, Negatives, and Ephemera
  - Photographic Prints., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographic Prints., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographic Prints., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Summer 1963] and "Circus" 1963 and Corresponding Negatives., Jun 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographic Prints and Corresponding Negatives., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographic Prints., 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographic Prints., 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographic Prints., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Masqurade HHC 1962". (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Group Shots]., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brochures and Holiday Greeting Cards (Higley Hill and Apple Hill)., 1962; 1963; 1965; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photograph Poster Boards (Oversize), 1997; undated (Flat-file 1, Drawer 7)
  - Scrapbook Pages [Reference copies from PHOTOS 239], 1946-1948 (Box OS006, Folder 1)
  - Photographs by Norma Holt, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- Series II - 70mm Slides.
  - "Indian Day"; "Olympics"; "Fiesta" and "Baseball - Bill Flemming"., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1 through 4)
  - "Picnick"; "Water Carnival"; "Basket Making"; "Carnival – Hilary"; "Carnival – Laura [?], Kim, Dana"; "Parents Day"; "Hair Combing – Minerva [?] A."; "Town Meeting"; "Kim – Cris – Theda Arts & Crafts"; "Carnival – Paul F., Bobby L."; "Parents Day – Hilary & Jrs [?]."; "Totem Pole – Hilary & Campers"., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1 through 3)
  - "Carnival 1959"; "Circus 1963"; "63"; "63 or 64"; "Lake Raponda"., 1959; 1963; 1964; undated (Box 2, Folder 1 through 4)
  - "Summer 1962 HHC: Marlboro Concert 16 st Apt. & Martha's Vineyard". (Box 2, Carton 1)
  - "Summer 1962 HHC Athletics". (Box 2, Carton 2)
  - "Camp 1963, Goat & Kids, Finions cast, Movie, Fair - 35mm ". (Box 2, Carton 3)
  - "Parents Day 1963". (Box 2, Carton 4)
  - "Summer 1964 Camp Indoor Carnival". (Box 2, Carton 5)
  - "Camp Photos Mikado – 1964". (Box 2, Carton 6)